Guide to the Teresa Carreño Papers, 1860-1991 (bulk 1860-1920)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Teresa Carreño Papers
1860-1991
1860-1920
Carreño, Teresa, 1853-1917
4.5 cubic feet (15 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Includes musical manuscripts of Carreño and others, such as Edward Macdowell, Amy Beach and Teresita Carreño-Tagliapietra; literary manuscripts of Carreño; letters to and from Carreño and to and from Marta Milinowski, her biographer; and a variety of scrapbooks, diaries and other materials relating to Carreño's life and professional career; Among the correspondents are Frances Macdowell, Gioachino Rossini, Edward Grieg, and Ede Poldini. There are also many articles about Carreño and programs of her concerts.
Biographical Note
Teresa Carreño was born in Caracas, Venezuela on December 22, 1853. She was the granddaughter of the Venezuelan composer Jose Cayetano Carreño. Her father, Manuel Antonio Carreño, was also a musician and composer. He was largely responsible for Teresa Carreño's early musical education and the documentation of the early years of her musical career.
When she was eight years old she was taken to New York where she studied with Gottschalk. Later, she also studied in Paris with Mathias and Anton Rubinstein. Her career was particularly successful in Germany where she lived and taught for over thirty years.
Throughout her life Carreño was recognized as a pianist, composer, conductor, and singer. She wrote many compositions for piano and one String Quartet in B minor. She also spent two years in Venezuela organizing and conducting an opera company in which she also sang.
Carreño died in New York on June 12, 1917.
The source for this brief biography is The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, vol. 3. (London: Macmillan Publishers Limited, 1980). See also Brian Mann's biographical sketch written for the 2003 Archives and Special Collections Library exhibit, Teresa Carreño: Walküre of the Piano.
Scope and Content Note
Includes musical manuscripts of Carreño and others, such as Edward MacDowell, Amy Beach and Teresita Carreño-Tagliapietra; literary manuscripts of Carreño; letters to and from Carreño and to and from Marta Milinowski, her biographer; and a variety of scrapbooks, diaries and other materials relating to Carreño's life and professional career; Among the correspondents are Frances Macdowell, Gioachino Rossini, Edward Grieg, and Ede Poldini. There are also many articles about Carreño and programs of her concerts.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
In his article on the Carreño Collection, MLA Notes (v 47, no 4), Brian Mann notes that Music Librarian, George Sherman Dickinson "must have been delighted, particularly given the hundreds of volumes of practical music it brought to his library." These hundreds of volumes, which also included books and periodical issues on music, were added to the main collection of the Music Library and are now almost indistinguishable from it save for the identifying stamp "Purchased from the Estate of Theresa [sic] Carreño." Since 2002 the Dickinson Music Library Carreño Collection consists of early published editions of music by Teresa Carreño, published music by other composers and dedicated or inscribed to Carreño, and orchestral music with performance annotations in Carreño's hand. For a listing of the published materials in the Music Library see the register of the George Sherman Dickinson Music Library Carreño Collection.
Register of the George Sherman Dickinson Music Library Carreño Collection
Photocopies of selected original music manuscript materials and correspondence in the Teresa Carreño Collection of the Special Collections Department in the Main Library of Vassar College have been placed in the Dickinson Music Library Carreño Collection in the Treasure Room.
Subject Headings
Names:
Macdowell, Frances; Rossini, Gioacchino, 1792-1868; Grieg, Edvard, 1843-1907; Poldini, Ede, 1869-1957; Milinowski, Marta, 1885-1970; Macdowell, Edward, 1860-1908; Beach, H. H. A., Mrs., 1867-1944; Carreño, Manuel Antonio, d. 1874; Carreño-Tagliapietra, Teresita
Subjects:
Concert programs; Music--Performance; Women composers; Women musicians; Pianists
Document Types:
Drawings (visual works); Diaries; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sheet music
VCL Categories:
Music
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, February 2007. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, October 2025.
Custodial History
Vassar Professor of Music, Marta Milinowski, studied with Carreño and wrote the first biography of the musician, Teresa Carreño, "By the Grace of God," (1940). Her connection brought about the purchase of a large number of materials from the Estate of Teresa Carreño through the Peabody Fund. A letter from the assistant Music Librarian, Natalie Mestechin, of 17 Sep 1943 notes: "On August 21, 1941 the Music Department made a purchase from the Estate of Theresa [sic] Carreño which included manuscripts, papers, photographs, music, costumes, etc., etc. and various books." In the mid-1950's selected materials were sent to the National Library in Caracas, Venezuela. At an unknown date other items were removed to the Special Collections Department of the Vassar College Libraries. In 1990, the materials that made up the Dickinson Music Library Carreño Collection at that time were researched and organized by Vassar Professor Brian Mann, assisted by Geoffrey Hills '91. His article, "The Carreño Collection at Vassar College," MLA Notes, 47 (1991), discusses the collection in detail as it existed at that point. Until 2002 the largest portion of the Teresa Carreño materials resided in the Dickinson Music Library. In 2002, all of the manuscript material and selected other materials were moved to the Archives and Special Collections Library of the Vassar College Libraries and integrated with the Carreño materials already housed there. In this process, separated parts were rejoined and additional materials came to light.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Dickinson Music Library, Vassar College, 2002.
Series List
- Series I. MUSIC MANUSCRIPTS, 1860-1914, undated; (Boxes 1-6)
- Series II. LITERARY MANUSCRIPTS, 1885-1886; (Box 7)
- Series III. CORRESPONDENCE, 1862-1939; (Boxes 8-9)
- Series IV. SCRAPBOOKS AND MEMORABILIA, 1862-1915; (Boxes 10-12)
- Series V. DIARY, DATE AND ADDRESS BOOK, 1897-[1917?]; (Box 13)
- Series VI. LEGAL DOCUMENTS, 1894-1915; (Box 14)
- Series VII. PRINTED MATERIALS AND PROGRAMS, 1863-1991, undated; (Box 14)
- Series VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS, undated; (Box 15)
- Series IX. ARTWORK, undated; (Box 15)
Container List
- SERIES I: MUSIC MANUSCRIPTS
  - By Teresa Carreño
    - Compositions with opus numbers
      - Reverie Impromptu Op. 3, undated (Folder 1.1)
      - Caprice Etude Op. 4, undated (Folder 1.2)
      - "Une Larme" Op. 5, undated (Folder 1.3)
      - Caprice-Etude Op. 6, undated (Folder 1.4)
      - Caprice-Etude Op. 7, undated (Folder 1.5)
      - "Souvenirs de mon pays" Op. 10, undated (Folder 1.6)
      - Marche Funèbre Op. 11, undated (Folder 1.7)
      - Prière Op. 12, undated (Folder 1.8)
      - "Sovenirs de L'Angleterre" Op. 16, undated (Folder 1.9)
      - (4éme Elégie) No. 4 Op. 20, undated (Folder 1.10)
      - (5éme Elégie) No. 5 Op. 21, undated (Folder 1.11)
      - (6éme Elégie) No. 6 Op. 22, undated (Folder 1.12)
      - Mazurka Op. 23, undated (Folder 1.13)
      - Vals Gayo Op. 38, undated (Folder 1.14)
    - Compositions without opus numbers
      - Serenade für Streich Orchester von Teresa Carreño, undated (Folder 2.1)
      - Hymnos al Bolivar, undated (Folder 2.2)
      - Etude-Mazurka, undated (Folder 2.3)
      - La Petite Boiteuse, undated (Folder 2.4)
      - Petite Berceuse, undated (Folder 2.5)
      - Feuillet D'Album. Lamartine (song), undated (Folder 2.6)
      - [No Title]. "Voga…" (song), undated (Folder 2.7)
      - Preludio and related sketches/copies, undated (Folder 2.8)
      - Composiciones de Maria Teresa Carreño, 1860-1861 (Folder 2.9)
      - "Mi Teresita" (Kleiner Walzer), undated (Folder 2.10)
    - Incomplete compositions, with titles and without opus numbers
      - 4éme Valse, undated (Folder 2.11)
      - Intermezzo-Scherzoso, undated (Folder 2.12)
      - Valse, undated (Folder 2.13)
      - [Valse Mélancholique], undated (Folder 2.14)
      - Romance, undated (Folder 2.15)
      - Romance, undated (Folder 2.16)
    - Sketch material (all presumably the work of Teresa Carreño)
      - 1-5. Sketches for String Quartet in B Minor, undated (Folder 2.17)
      - 6-17. Unidentified Sketches, undated (Folder 2.18)
      - Harmony and Counterpoint Exercises. [May also be by her students], (7 items) (Folder 2.19)
  - By and about Manuel Antonio Carreño
    - Cours Complet, undated (Folder 3.1)
    - Exercises. Première partie, undated (Folder 3.2)
    - Deuxième Partie. Rapports proportionnels, undated (Folder 3.3)
    - Deuxième Partie. Tierces brisés, undated (Folder 3.4)
    - Troisième Partie, undated (Folder 3.5)
    - Quatrième Partie, undated (Folder 3.6)
    - Cinquième Partie, undated (Folder 3.7)
    - Cours Complet, undated (Folder 3.8)
    - Partie Supplementaire. Exercises, undated (Folder 3.9)
    - Observations Générales written by M. Marmontel, undated (Folder 3.10)
    - Gymnastique vocale, undated (Folder 3.11)
    - An untitled set of theoretical writings, with music examples, paginated 1-23, undated (Folder 3.12)
    - Various studies in piano technique, undated (Folder 3.13)
    - L'absence Valse pour piano, undated (Folder 3.14)
    - Etude Mazurka pour piano, undated; (2 copies) (Folder 3.15)
  - Teresita Carreño-Tagliapietra
    - [No Title] "Allegro energico", undated (Folder 4.1)
    - Berceuse per Teresita Tagliapietra (Incomplete), undated (Folder 4.2)
    - Elegie, undated (Folder 4.3)
    - Minuetto in Stilo Antico, undated (Folder 4.4)
    - Notturno, undated; (fragment) (Folder 4.5)
    - Tristesse, undated (Folder 4.6)
  - Edward MacDowell
    - Autograph for Op. 18. [sic] Op. 17, undated (Folder 4.7)
    - Autograph for Op. 19. [sic] Op. 18, undated (Folder 4.8)
    - Autograph for Op. 23, undated (Folder 4.9)
    - Autograph for Op. 23, undated (Folder 4.10)
    - Autograph for Op. 24, undated (Folder 4.11)
    - Autograph for Op. 36, undated (Folder 4.12)
  - Amy Beach
    - Concerto for piano and orchestra, op. 45. Score, undated (Folder 5.1)
    - Concerto for piano and orchestra, op. 45. Parts, undated (Folder 5.2)
  - Various Composers
    - d'Albert, Eugene. Annotated proofs: Der Mensch und das Leben, op 14. (parts) [Orch. B. 949], Zweites Quartet [Bote & Bock 13749], Der Rubin [20305; Breitkopf & Härtel], undated (Folder 6.1)
    - Chopin, Frederic. Concerto in E minor for piano and orchestra, op 11, dedicated to Carreño and arranged by A. Munckheimer, undated (Folder 6.2)
    - [Fielten? Fielsen? Firlten?] Rigadoon (Rigandon) for Pianoforte T. P. "Oxford 1908", undated (Folder 6.3)
    - Jordan, Pierre. Klavierstukker op. 3 no. II Grokeske, undated (Folder 6.4)
    - Schindler, Kurt. Letztes Wiegenlied Eine Romanze von Emmy Destinn, 1899 (Folder 6.5)
    - Stow, G.G. " A few lines of welcome to Mme Teresa Carreño,", 17 April 1914 (Folder 6.6)
    - Tagliapietra, Giovanni. Los lindos ojos de Y. Ferrer, undated (Folder 6.7)
    - Watson, Regina. Bourée l'antique, undated (Folder 6.8)
    - Watson, Regina. Cradle Song, undated (Folder 6.9)
    - Watson, Regina. Sérénade orientale, undated (Folder 6.10)
- SERIES II. LITERARY MANUSCRIPTS
  - Extracts from Caracas -- Childhood and Visit, 1885-1886; (6 items) (Folder 7.1)
  - Extracts from Caracas -- Childhood and Visit, 1885-1886; (7 items) (Folder 7.2)
  - Carreño's manuscript, Possibilities of Tone Color and 2 clean, unbound proofs, undated (Folder 7.3)
  - Typescript of Carreño's wartime experiences, undated (Folder 7.4)
  - Unpublished writings about Carreño, undated; (8 items) (Folder 7.5)
  - Literary materials Honoring Teresa Carreño, undated (Folder 7.6)
  - Geneology of Carreño by Rafael Mirabal Ponce, undated (Folder 7.7)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - From Teresa Carreño, 1909, 1916; (2 letters) (Folder 8.1)
    - From Teresa Carreño, undated; (15 letters) (Folder 8.2)
    - From Teresa Carreño, undated; (28 letters) (Folder 8.3)
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Gottschalk, Maurice, 1862; (1 letter) (Folder 8.4)
    - Grieg, Edward, 1902, undated; (2 letters) (Folder 8.5)
    - Lehmann, Lilli, 1899, 1916, undated; (3 letters) (Folder 8.6)
    - MacDowell, Edward (to TC and others), 1897-1902; (4 letters) (Folder 8.7)
    - MacDowell, Fannie, 1907-1916; (17 letters) (Folder 8.8)
    - MacDowell, Fannie, 1895-1909; (14 letters) (Folder 8.9)
    - MacDowell, Frances, 1908; (1 letter) (Folder 8.10)
    - MacDowell, Frances, 1892-1908; (11 letters) (Folder 8.11)
    - MacDowell, Frances, undated; (10 letters) (Folder 8.12)
    - MacDowell, Marian, 1907-1908, undated; (4 letters) (Folder 8.13)
    - MacDowell, Marian, undated; (4 letters) (Folder 8.14)
    - Paur, Emir, 1895-1897; (3 letters) (Folder 9.1)
    - Poldini, Ede, 1908-1910; (3 letters) (Folder 9.2)
    - Saint-Saens, Camille, 1894-1914; (3 letters) (Folder 9.3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1869-1898; (5 letters) (Folder 9.4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1901-1909; (19 letters) (Folder 9.5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1910-1912; (6 letters) (Folder 9.6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1912-1915; (6 letters) (Folder 9.7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1916; (5 letters) (Folder 9.8)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; (2 letters) (Folder 9.9)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; (6 cards) (Folder 9.10)
    - Various authors, Recipients include A. Tagliapietra and G. Novaes, 1918-1920, 1931; (13 letters) (Folder 9.11)
    - Various authors. "Letters quoted,", undated; (43 letters) (Folder 9.12)
  - Letters about Teresa Carreño
    - Rossini, Giaocchini, 1862-1866; (3 letters) (Folder 9.13)
    - de Sola, Vincent, 1938-1939; (7 letters) (Folder 9.14)
  - To and from Marta Milinowski
    - Calcaño y Calcaño, José Antonio, undated (Folder 9.15)
    - Corson, James, undated (Folder 9.16)
    - Dodge, Rudolf, undated (Folder 9.17)
    - Guerra, Alirio Diez, undated (Folder 9.18)
    - Harris, Teresita, undated (Folder 9.19)
    - Weber, Hertha, undated (Folder 9.20)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 9.21)
- SERIES IV. SCRAPBOOKS AND MEMORABILIA
  - Autograph album including Carreño's signature, undated (Folder 10.1)
  - Guest book: 11 entries from include G. Sonneck, Marion Bauer, 1911-1915 (Folder 10.2)
  - "Important Papers" (Passenger list, Marriage announcement, Written account, Last words), undated (Folder 10.3)
  - Commendation, 1893 (Folder 10.4)
  - Scrapbook I (red, leather bound), 1862 May-1868 Jul (Folder 11.1)
  - Scrapbook II (card board and leather), 1872-1885 (Folder 12.1)
  - Scrapbook " To Mme Teresa Carreño from Sadie Gottlieb,", undated (Folder 12.2)
- SERIES V. DIARY, DATE, AND ADDRESS BOOKS
  - Address book (in black leather clutch), includes calling cards with brief notes, undated (Folder 13.1)
  - Appointment book (removed from black leather clutch) concerts, lessons, and other appointments, [1917?] (Folder 13.2)
  - "Prontuario,", 1897-1912 (Folder 13.3)
- SERIES VI. LEGAL DOCUMENTS
  - Birth records, 1894 (Folder 14.1)
  - Concert contract, 1899 (Folder 14.1)
  - Deposition for her daughter, [1913?] (Folder 14.1)
  - Official document, 1915 (Folder 14.1)
- SERIES VII. PRINTED MATERIALS AND PROGRAMS
  - Articles about Carreño, [1867?]-1991; (12 items) (Folder 14.2)
  - Articles about Carreño, undated; (15 items) (Folder 14.3)
  - Articles about Carreño in German, undated; (8 items) (Folder 14.4)
  - Articles about Carreño's death, 1917; (15 items) (Folder 14.5)
  - Articles and anecdotes, undated (Folder 14.6)
  - "Articles of exceptional interest; sources,", undated (Folder 14.7)
  - Concert programs various years, 1863-1918 (Folder 14.8)
  - Concert programs: printed and handwritten, undated (Folder 14.9)
  - News clippings: Milinowski's groupings, undated (Folder 14.10)
  - Programs for Carreño's concerts, undated; (6 items) (Folder 14.11)
  - Teresita Blois and Eugen D'Albert: concert programs and articles, undated (Folder 14.12)
- SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Photos, undated (Folder 15.1)
  - Photos of Teresita Blois, undated (Folder 15.2)
  - Marta Milinowski's photo layouts, undated (Folder 15.3)
  - Marta Milinowski's photo layouts, undated (Folder 15.4)
- SERIES IX. ARTWORK
  - Drawings, undated; (3 items) (Folder 15.5)